James Ivey Collection
James Ivey Collection
1892-1971
1966-1969
Ivey, Jim.
2.1 linear ft.
Original editorial cartoons by Jim Ivey, a collection of cartoons by other cartoonists and two catalogs.
2651126
Biographical History
James Burnett Ivey (1925- ), commonly known as Jim Ivey, is an American cartoonist and cartoon historian.
James Ivey was born in Chattanooga, Tennessee on April 15, 1925, the son of a college professor. He attended the University of Louisville, George Washington University and the National Art School in Washington, D.C and also pursued correspondence work through Landon School of Illustration and Cartooning. While a Navy submariner from 1943 to 1946, Ivey also drew cartoons.
Ivey began as a layout artist in the engraving department at the Washington Star before he landed a spot in the Star’s editorial art department. In 1953 he left for the St. Petersburg Times, and from 1959 to 1966 Ivey held a cartoonist position at the San Francisco Examiner. Ivey then pursued freelance work until he became a cartoonist with the Orlando Sentinel in 1970 where he stayed until 1977 when he again went back to freelancing. Ivey also spent time teaching the art of cartooning at the University of Central Florida from 1978 to 1983.
Ivey is also well known as a cartoon collector and comics historian. In the 1950s, Ivey received a Reid Fellowship to study political cartooning in Europe and returned to the United States in 1959. In 1967, Ivey opened the Cartoon Museum with items from his own collection and published the quarterly publication cARTtoon. In the 1970s he started the annual Orlandocon convention. Ivey’s interest has spanned all forms of cartooning including comic books and his personal collection of cartoons is international in scope. His writings have appeared regularly in the World of Comic Art, the Comics Journal and Hogan’s Alley and his own work has been included in several books including Thoughts of Man (1975) and his self published retrospective, Cartoons I Liked (2008).
Ivey’s cartoons have been reprinted in other countries though Germany’s Tarantel-Press and were also distributed through the Chicago Tribune and Rotcho syndicates. Ivey was an active member of the American Association of Editorial Cartoonists and the National Cartoonists Society and won the NCS’s Silver T-Square Award in 1979.
Jim Ivey currently lives in Orlando, Florida and continues to draw freelance cartoons.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The James Ivey Collection is divided into 2 series: Cartoons and Catalogs. Cartoons contains 72 original editorial cartoons by Ivey (1951-1971) as well as 60 cartoons by other cartoonists (these include editorial cartoons, comic strips and magazine cartoons from 1892-1969).
Ivey's cartoons primarily address local and state issues in Florida including education and taxes as well as state and federal elections. Of particular interest are two cartoons depicting William Safire, who was hired by the Florida Development Commission in 1967. Generally, few words accompanied his cartoons. Ivey's style featured loose, bold lines and relied heavily on caricature and humor, a style noticeably different from other editorial cartoonists during this period. For example, one cartoon commenting on the rise of automation industry depicted children meeting an automated Santa Claus during Christmastime.
Ivey's cartoons were drawn with pen, ink and blue pencil on paper and illustration board (and some paper affixed to illustration board) and unlike most editorial and political cartoonists during this time he did not use crayon. Some have dot screening attached. Ivey's work for the Orlando Sentinel often contains sticky notes with notations about the size, page and day the cartoon was to be published.
Also included in the collection are original cartoons from other cartoonists that Ivey collected. Heavily represented in Ivey's collection of other cartoonists are cartoonists from other Florida newspapers including Lynn Brudon and Richard Hodgins Sr. Additionally there are several of examples of work from European cartoonists.
Catalogs consists of 2 items- a catalog detailing Ivey's collection of American and international cartoons (from his Cartoon Museum) and a catalog from the 1971 exhibit, "Hogarth to Herblock" at the Lock Haven Art Center.
Arrangement of the Collection
Cartoons drawn by Ivey are arranged in date order. Cartoons by other cartoonists are arranged in alphabetical order by the cartoonist's last name.
Related Material
Cartoonists
Eugene Craig
,
Richard Hodgins, Sr.
and
Jack Kent
who are represented in the James Ivey Collection also have cartoons in other collections at.
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Brudon, Lynn.; Hodgins, Sr., Richard; Ivey, Jim.; Methfessel, Karl.; Safire, William, 1929-2009 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Orlando sentinel.; Orlando star.; San Francisco examiner.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Cartoonists -- Florida.; Cartoonists -- California -- San Francisco.; Editorial cartoons -- California.; Editorial cartoons -- Florida.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Education -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Taxation -- Caricatures and cartoons.; World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Florida -- Politics and government -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Catalogs (documents); Editorial cartoons.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of James Ivey, 1967-1970 and 1972.
One 1965 San Francisco Examiner cartoon, gift of Janet Wolfertz, 2013.
Inventory
- Cartoons
  - By Jim Ivey
    - Pocket Cartoons, 1951; 1962,; undated (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
    - St. Petersburg Times, 1956; 1958 (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
    - San Francisco Examiner, 1965; undated (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
      One cartoon gift of Janet Wolfertz, 2013.
    - St. Petersburg Times, 1966 (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
      28 Jul 1966
    - St. Petersburg Times, 1967 (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
      1967 (no month or day, 4 items); 19 Feb 1967; 19 Apr 1967; 6 May 1967; 16 May 1967; 8 Dec 1967
    - St. Petersburg Times, 1968 (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
      1968 (no month or day, 5 items); 3 Jan 1968; 27 Jan 1968; 11 Mar 1968; 20 Oct 1968
    - St. Petersburg Times, 1969 (Oversize 1, Folder 7)
      1969 (no month or day, 1 item); 12 Jan 1969; 19 Jan 1969; 9 Feb 1969; 23 Mar 1969; 23 Apr 1969; 1 Jun 1969; 6 Jul 1969; 16 Jul 1969; 20 Jul 1969; 10 Aug 1969; 13 Aug 1969; 20 Aug 1969; 21 Sep 1969; 28 Sep 1969; 12 Oct 1969; 20 Oct 1969
    - Orlando Star, 1970 (Oversize 1, Folder 8)
      1970 (no month or day, 7 items); 4 Feb 1970; 2 Jul 1970; 10 Jul 1970
    - Orlando Evening Star and Orlando Sentinel, 1971 (Oversize 1, Folder 9)
      1971 (no month or day, 4 items); 22 Dec 1971
    - Miscelleneous items, undated; most are probably from the St. Petersburg Times (Oversize 1, Folder 10)
  - By others
    - Addis, Don, St. Pete Independent, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Bart(olomew), Minneapolis Journal, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Brown, Pat, Orlando Sentinel, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Brudon, Lynn, Orlando Sentinel, 1964; 1968-1969 (Oversize 2)
      15 Jul 1964; 6 May 1968; 1 Jun 1968; 24 Mar 1969; 12 Aug 1968; 25 Sep 1964; 7 May 1965; 10 Jun 1968; 15 Jul 1968; 30 Sep 1968; 14 Oct 1968; 28 Oct 1968; 18 Nov 1968; 23 Dec 1968; 9 Dec 1968; 16 Dec 1968; 6 Jan 1969; 10 Feb 1969; 24 Feb 1969; 25 May (no year); 22 Jun (no year)
    - Costello, Jerry, Knickerbocker News (Albany, NY), 8 Sep (no year) (Oversize 2)
    - Coulthard, John, circa 1930s; cartoon ad (Oversize 2)
    - Craig, Eugene, Columbus Dispatch, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Dalrymple, Louis, Puck, 1892 (Oversize 2)
    - Dean, Odel, Dayton News (Oversize 2)
      circa 1910; circa 1920
    - Egli, Leo, Licking County Weekly, 1951 (Oversize 2)
    - Evans, Ray, Columbus Dispatch, circa 1956 (Oversize 2)
    - Glackens, L.M., Puck, 3 Feb 1909 (Oversize 2)
    - Gunder, Ed, Brevard Sentinel, 1966-1967 (Oversize 2)
      6 Apr 1966; 21 Nov 1967; 2 Dec 1967
    - Hodgins Sr., Richard, Orlando Star, 1969-1970 (Oversize 2)
      4 Feb 1969; 7 Mar 1969; 27 Mar 1969; 28 May 1969; 4 Jun 1969; 23 Jun 1969; 14 Oct 1969; 3 Dec 1969; 13 Jan 1970; 26 Jan 1970
    - Kelly, Charles, Dublin [Ireland] Opinion, 23 Jan 1965 (Oversize 2)
    - Kent, Jack, 23 Jan 1965; comic strip (Oversize 2)
    - Maris, A.M., Punch Bowl, 1908; University of Pennsylvania humor magazine (Oversize 2)
    - Methfessel, Karl, Korean Stars and Stripes, undated; 6 items, mostly from the Korean Stars and Stripes; includes one work in paint of a soldier (Oversize 2)
    - Meyer, Gil, Orlando Sentinel (Oversize 2)
      1966; 24 May 1969
    - Rudolph, circa 1920 (Oversize 2)
    - Somerville, John, 8 Apr 1964; comic strip, Two Bits, San Francisco News Call Bulletin (Oversize 2)
    - Stinson, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Wood, Art, Pittsburgh Press, 1962 (Oversize 2)
- Catalogs
  - Cartoon Museum, undated (1)
  - The Cartoon - Hogarth to Herblock- Lock Haven Art Center, Aug 1971 (1)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, F= Folder. For example: B1F1= Box 1 Folder 1.
Agnew, Spiro T. B1F9
American Indians B1F6 B1F8
automation B1F1 B1F3
Bafalis, Louis A. B1F6
Britain B1F2
California B1F3
CBS B1F8
China B1F3
Collins, Edward B1F6 B1F10
communism B1F8
Cramer, William B1F6-B1F7 B1F10
Democratic Party B1F5
drug use B1F9
Dubček, Alexander B1F8
Eckerd, Jack B1F6
education B1F5-B1F7 B1F10
elections B1F6-B1F7 B1F10
Everglades B1F4 B1F7
Florida B1F4-B1F10
Gurney, Leroy B1F6 B1F10
Holland, Spessard B1F7
Humphrey, Hubert B1F6 B1F8
Iceland B1F2
industry (general) B1F5
insurance B1F7
judicial system B1F7
Kirk, Claude B1F5 B1F10
lottery B1F5
Meany, George B1F1 B1F9
Meir, Golda B1F9
Middle East B1F9
NATO B1F2 B1F9
Nhu, Ngo Dinh B1F3
Nixon, Richard M. B1F8-B1F9
O'Brien, Larry B1F8
organized crime B1F10
polio B1F2
population B1F3
Public Service Commission B1F7
Republican Party B1F5-B1F7
Sadat, Anwar B1F9
Safire, William B1F5
Sukarno B1F1
taxes B1F5-B1F6 B1F8 B1F10
transit and transportation B1F7 B1F10
Turlington, Ralph B1F7 B1F10
United Nations B1F3
Unruh, Jesse B1F3
Vietnam War B1F3 B1F8
voting B1F1
voting rights B1F9
wage and price controls B1F8-B1F6
Wallace, George B1F6
women B1F8